Hi book lovers,
my name is Mek and I run OpenLibrary.org
over at the Internet Archive.
For those who aren't familiar, the Internet
Archive is a nonprofit here in San
Francisco, California, which is probably
most famous for the Wayback Machine.
The Wayback Machine is this mind-blowing
website that lets you go back in time
and see a website as it was up to 20 years ago.
So if I type in google.com into the
Wayback Machine, then I go back to
February 1999,
then I can see what Google used to look
like and things have changed
a whole ton since then.
Many people don't know that in addition
to running the Wayback Machine, the Internet Archive
is also a California state accredited digital library
and we have more than 4 million books that are publicly
accessible or that you can borrow
directly from your computer using
OpenLibrary.org.
So Open Library has more than 4 million books.
Some of them are publicly accessible and
you can read them right in your browser
and some of them require borrowing through
our controlled digital lending system.
So if you happen to see a book that
strikes your fancy, maybe The Hitchhiker's
Guide to the Galaxy,
then we can click on it and we will be brought
to a books page.
The books page will give you
the opportunity to preview the
book, to borrow the book.
You don't need a special
library card to read or
borrow a book on OpenLibrary.org.
You just need an email
address and once you sign up,
you'll be able to borrow for free.
In this case, why don't we click on
preview and we'll get a few pages of the
front matter, table of contents,
copyright page, and also the back page.
And once we're confident this is the book
that we want to borrow, we can either
click on the borrow button or there's also
a listen option, which is kind of like
Siri, which uses your web browser's
high-quality Google or Apple voices to
read the book to you as if it's an audiobook.
So why don't we go ahead and borrow
the book and it should pop open the book
reader. There's a few different ways to
borrow the book.
The first one is offline reading.
If you click PDF or EPUB, then you're
presented with an option to use a form of
protected DRM to read a PDF or EPUB
offline for two weeks and during that time
you're the only person who can access the book.
And it's done through a piece of
software called Adobe Digital Editions.
Another option that we have is using the
read aloud feature. So why don't we flip
to the beginning of a chapter here and
if you click the speaker button in the
lower right-hand corner of the book,
you'll see that it activates this read aloud
control panel. And why don't we press
play, hear what that sounds like.
"Chapter 4 Far away on the opposite spiral arm
of the Galaxy, five hundred thousand light years
from the star Sol, Zaphod Beeblebrox, president
of the Imperial Galactic Government,
sped across the seas of Damogran, his ion drive
delta boat winking and flashing in the Damogran sun."
So if that's a little too slow for you,
you can speed it up to 1.25 or 1.5x.
"Chapter 4 Far away on the opposite spiral arm"
"Chapter 4 Far away on the opposite spiral arm of the"
All right. In addition to being able to
read offline, read normally, or also to
use the audio controls,
we have the search inside feature. So if there's
a quote we're trying to remember from a book,
let's see if I got it right, then
we should see, these pins on the navigation
bar that correlate to the matches
within the book. I click it and I see the
famous "So long and thanks for all the
fish." Now I can either click the back
button and return to Open Library or even
though I have 13 days left on my loan,
I can click return book, which I'm gonna
do so that someone else might enjoy it.
And once the book is returned, it will
bring me back to OpenLibrary.org.
I'm presented with a Goodreads style button
that allows me to mark this book either
as want to read, that I've already read
it, or currently reading. I'm gonna
click currently reading so that I can
save that in my book log.
And I could also choose a number
of stars if I want to rate it.
Up on the top of the website,
there's a tab called My Books, which lets me
navigate to my loans,
or also to see all of the books on my
reading log. So I'm gonna click that.
Here I see a list of all of the
books that are on my reading log.
And if I want to, I can manage the privacy
settings and share this with a friend
so they can see what I'm reading.
In some cases, you'll notice that a book
does not have a read or borrow button
because it has not yet been acquired or
digitized. And this is where you can step in.
Everyone in the world has an opportunity
to be a part of Open Library and make
titles available by sponsoring a book.
If you go to OpenLibrary.org slash
sponsorship or click this button,
you'll be presented with information
on how you can sponsor a book.
If you look through the available titles,
you might find that there's a book on
Frida and you happen to be an enthusiast
for Mexican culture. And so if you click
the sponsor button, you'll be presented
with a page where you can make a tax
deductible donation. Within one month,
the book will be purchased, shipped,
digitized, and made available on OpenLibrary.org,
and you'll have the opportunity
to be the first to borrow the book and to
also have a message publicly display on
OpenLibrary.org
as the donor should you wish to. Back on
Open Library, you can also take advantage
of our search functionality. So you
might search for a book by title
like Gödel, Escher, Bach, or
similarly, you can search by author.
And here you'll see all of the
books that we have by J.K. Rowling.
Let's choose Harry Potter
and the Philosopher's Stone.
So now we're on a works page and it shows
all of the different editions of this
book that are available, from Greek to
Russian to Chinese to Latin to Spanish and
even Latvian, and of course, a handful of
books in English as well. If we select
one of the editions, we'll be brought
back to the book page where we again,
can preview or borrow. And if we click
on the edition count in the upper left
hand corner, we'll be brought back to
the works page.
And if you are a teacher or
a parent, an educator, librarian,
you can use the browse functionality to
see a listing of all subjects, which span
fiction to nonfiction, books on science
and mathematics, including textbooks on
biology, chemistry, children's books,
stories and rhyme, picture books, bedtime
books, history books,
biographies and autobiographies.
I hope you've enjoyed this tour of Open
Library. Not only are we a non-profit
project, we're also an open source project.
And that means over a hundred people
from around the world have helped contribute
to make OpenLibrary.org the world's
library.
That is Amsterdam, New Zealand, Toronto, India,
Massachusetts, California and beyond.
Especially today, as libraries and
schools across the country and world are
shutting down, the Internet Archive is
committed to making our information as
broadly, publicly accessible as possible.
If you would like to contribute to
OpenLibrary.org or if you have any
questions about our service, don't hesitate
and send me an email at mek,
that's M-E-K @ archive.org.
We'd be delighted to hear from you.
Thanks for taking a look at Open Library at
the Internet Archive and happy reading.